foreign
[Music]
suppose we want to walk from the point 0
0 to the point n comma n Only traveling
north and east and not passing below
this diagonal Y equals X
this problem consists of counting what
are called the Northeast integer lattice
paths and they look like this
in a previous video I enumerated lots of
these and showed how to find a recursive
formula for counting the number of such
lattice paths
right here we see that the first view
values of this sequence are one one two
five Fourteen and here we see the 42
lattice paths traveling from 0 0 to 5 5.
as I said we know already how to find a
recursion for this sequence but if we
let C sub n be the number of such
lattice pass to n comma n can we now
find a closed formula for this integer
sequence
here's one way to provide a closed
formula for the number of such paths
here we let N equal 5 represent the
general situation instead of counting
the restricted lattice paths we can
first enumerate all the lattice paths
traveling Northeast they go from 0 0 to
n n in a previous video I showed that
this is counted by a binomial
coefficient but we want to avoid the
paths that pass below Y equals X those
must be the ones that intersect this
line y equals x minus 1.
for each such path that intersects the
red line we can reflect the remaining
part of the path after the first
intersection across that line
here we do it with all of the lines that
we don't want to include in our final
count
[Music]
as we reflect and remove the bad lattice
paths we notice something special about
all of these Reflections look at what
happens to the end point of these
lattice paths they all seem to be
hitting on the same point so what we're
getting from this collection of
reflected lattice paths seems to be a
collection of lattice paths that still
starts at the origin zero zero but this
time ends at a different point
in fact all of the reflected lattice
paths end at the point n plus 1 comma n
minus 1 which is the reflection of the
point n n over the red dotted line but
now if we enumerate all the Northeast
lattice paths from 0 0 to the point n
plus 1 comma n minus one we see that
each of them crosses the red dotted line
and therefore must have been one of the
reflected paths because the reflection
process is invertible we see there's a
one-to-one correspondence between the
bad paths traveling to n comma n and all
of the paths traveling to n plus one
comma n minus one but now we have our
strategy to count the good lattice paths
the ones from 0 0 to NN traveling
Northeast and not passing below the
diagonal in order to do this we must
first have all the paths that travel
Northeast from 0 0 to NN as I mentioned
before this is counted by the binomial
coefficient 2N choose n then we're going
to subtract all of the bad paths but we
know that those correspond to the
Northeast lattice paths traveling from 0
0 to n plus one comma n minus 1 which is
also counted by the binomial coefficient
2N choose n plus one but then we can use
binomial coefficient identities and
formulas to see that c sub n is equal to
1 divided by n plus 1 times 2N choose n
this is a closed formula for the
sequence c n which are known as the
Catalan numbers
you can find this result in any standard
text describing the Catalan numbers